<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Drafts on Kabads</title><link>https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft.html</link><description>Recent content in Drafts on Kabads</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SELinux Permissions</title><link>https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft/2019-12-30-selinux.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft/2019-12-30-selinux.html</guid><description>SELinux (Security Enhanced Linux) is a linux kernel security module that provides a mechanism for supporting access control policies. This can support the protection from tampering and bypassing threats that might be possible with certain applications. SELinux checks permissions after the usual operating system permissions (user, groups and read/write/execute policies). If the local permissions succeeds, then SELinux checks for permissions.
A Linux kernel that uses SELinux enforces mandatory access control policies that confine user programs and system services, also including file and network resources.</description></item><item><title>How to Create Virtual Machines With Qemu</title><link>https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft/2019-11-11-how-to-create-virtual-machines-qemu.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 13:52:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft/2019-11-11-how-to-create-virtual-machines-qemu.html</guid><description>This post outlines the steps needed to create a qemu environment within a machine and install virtual machines in that environment.
Software required:
qemu-kvm libvirt virt-install virt-manager virt-manager is a graphical interface to the resources, and is optional according to whether you run a graphical interface.
Networking One of the important tasks before installing a virtual machine is to set up the virtual networking. This means that as the VM installs, it can work with the networking.</description></item><item><title>Ruby Arrays</title><link>https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft/2019-07-29-arrays-with-ruby.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft/2019-07-29-arrays-with-ruby.html</guid><description>Ruby has extensive coverage for arrays (sometimes called lists if you are coming from a Python background). Arrays are for collecting information all in one place, or in a list. Arrays are sequential, which means that they don&amp;rsquo;t change order once set. Arrays are mutable (they can change items in the list).
Declaring an Array Here is an example of an array:
scores = [14, 12, 4, 20, 19] These scores can be for a particular person in a particular test or activity.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft/2021-06-26-testing.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kabads.monkeez.org/draft/2021-06-26-testing.html</guid><description>This is a test and I&amp;rsquo;m interested I really want to switch to hugo.</description></item></channel></rss>