<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ruby on Kabads</title>
    <link>//home.monkeez.org/hugo/categories/ruby.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in ruby on Kabads</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//home.monkeez.org/hugo/categories/ruby/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ruby Arrays</title>
      <link>//home.monkeez.org/hugo/draft/2019-07-29-arrays-with-ruby.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//home.monkeez.org/hugo/draft/2019-07-29-arrays-with-ruby.html</guid>
      <description>Ruby has extensive coverage for arrays (sometimes called lists if you are coming from a Python background). Arrays are for collecting information all in one place, or in a list. Arrays are sequential, which means that they don&amp;rsquo;t change order once set. Arrays are mutable (they can change items in the list).
Declaring an Array Here is an example of an array:
scores = [14, 12, 4, 20, 19]  These scores can be for a particular person in a particular test or activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Case Statements in Ruby - Learning Ruby 3</title>
      <link>//home.monkeez.org/hugo/2019/07/18/Case-Statements-in-Ruby-Learning-Ruby-3.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//home.monkeez.org/hugo/2019/07/18/Case-Statements-in-Ruby-Learning-Ruby-3.html</guid>
      <description>If you are coming from using python, then you will be used to using a lot of if...elif...else statements to catch conditions in variables. Sometimes this can be tedious - in Ruby it is easier to use case statements.
Let&amp;rsquo;s assume that you are checking for ages of people and want to classify them according to their age (it might be a sceranio of runners in a race and you want to find out who won each age range).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strings in Ruby - Learning Ruby 2</title>
      <link>//home.monkeez.org/hugo/2019/07/12/Strings-in-Ruby-Learning-Ruby-2.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//home.monkeez.org/hugo/2019/07/12/Strings-in-Ruby-Learning-Ruby-2.html</guid>
      <description>Ruby has great string support. This post summarises the functions that are available.
This is not designed to be a tutorial for others, but rather a record for myself in learning Ruby.
.downcase This method turns any characters in a string to lowercase.
a = &amp;quot;My String&amp;quot;.downcase  returns
&amp;quot;my string&amp;quot;  .upcase .upcase method does the opposite of downcase. It will change the case of any lowercase characters to uppercase.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning Ruby - First Impressions</title>
      <link>//home.monkeez.org/hugo/2019/06/21/Learning-Ruby-First-Impressions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//home.monkeez.org/hugo/2019/06/21/Learning-Ruby-First-Impressions.html</guid>
      <description>Chef is used in my place of work, and so as a result I started learning Ruby programming language. I know some python (enough to get me by) but thought that knowing some Ruby would be a good development in my learning. This is an attempt an my first impressions of what is good for a beginner and what is not so good (from the perspective of someone coming from Python).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
